In 1964 a group of seven year old children were interviewed for the documentary
"Seven Up". They've been filmed every seven years since. Now they are 56.
56 Up is a documentary film directed by Michael Apted.
When a cross-section of seven-year-olds were interviewed for 7 Up in 1964 it was immediately
evident that their social backgrounds influenced their attitudes towards life.
While the upper class children were confident and self-assured, those from middle and
working class backgrounds were resigned to a challenging life of hard work.
This premise was put to the test every seven years when the same group
were interviewed about the progression of their lives.
49 years in the making, the changes that occurred to the original 14 make for
fascinating television and are in many ways the stories of all our lives.
From success and disappointment, marriage and childbirth, to poverty and
illness, nearly every facet of life has been captured on film.
Now, at the age of 56, the group are once more brought together and, with the benefit of hindsight,
assess whether their lives have been ruled by circumstance or self-determination.
Self, played by Peter Davies.
Self, played by Neil Hughes.
Self, played by Tony Walker.
Self, played by Lynn Johnson.
Self, played by Susan Sullivan.
Self, played by Jacqueline Bassett.
The Up series of documentary films follows the lives of ten boys and four girls
in England, beginning in 1964, when they were seven years old.
The first film was titled Seven Up!, with later films adjusting the number in the
title to match the age of the subjects at the time of filming.
The documentary has had nine episodes—one every
seven years—thus spanning 56 years.
The series has been produced by Granada Television for ITV, which has broadcast
all of them except 42 Up (1998), which was broadcast on BBC One.
Individual films and the series as a whole have received numerous accolades; in 1991, the then-latest
instalment, 28 Up, was chosen for Roger Ebert's list of the ten greatest films of all time.
The series was voted the most influential British TV programme of the past
50 years, in a 2024 poll of the Broadcasting Press Guild.
The children were selected for the original programme to represent the range of socio-economic backgrounds in
Britain at that time, on the assumption that each child's social class would determine their future.
The first instalment was made as a one-off edition of Granada Television's series, World in Action, directed by Canadian Paul Almond, with involvement by "a fresh-faced young
researcher, a middle-class Cambridge graduate", Michael Apted, whose role in the initial programme included "trawling the nation's schools for 14 suitable subjects".
About the first programme, Apted has said:It was Paul's film ...
but he was more interested in making a beautiful film about being seven, whereas I wanted to make a nasty
piece of work about these kids who have it all, and these other kids who have nothing.
After Almond's direction of the original programme, director Michael Apted continued the series with new
instalments every seven years, filming material from those of the fourteen who chose to participate.
The aim of the continuing series is stated at the beginning of 7 Up as: "We brought these
children together because we wanted a glimpse of England in the year 2000.
The shop's steward and the executive of the year 2000 are now seven years old." The most
recent instalment, the ninth, titled 63 Up, premiered in the UK on ITV in 2019.
A special episode featuring celebrity fans of the
series, 7 Up & Me, also aired on ITV in 2019.
Apted is reported to have said, "I hope to do 84 Up when
I'll be 99"; however, he died in 2021.
In July 2025 it was confirmed that the series will continue with a new director,
Richard Denton, for the next instalment, 70 Up, to be released in 2026.